Guide to the Florence Marryat Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Florence Marryat collection
1833-1905
GEN MSS 994
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, literary manuscripts, printed ephemera, photographs, drawings and watercolors, scrapbooks, and other papers documenting the life and career of English author and actress Florence Marryat. Visual materials include a wide selection of portraits of Marryat, and drawings and photographs from her time living in South Asia with her first husband; among those are a watercolor portrait of the martyred Sergeant-Major John Lilley (died while imprisioned in Mhow, 1862). Many of Marryat's correspondents were figures in the British literary and theater communities, including Charles Dickens and George Augustus Sala; a scrapbook of letters holds several portrait photographs of those who wrote to her. Also present is material related to Marryat's father, novelist Frederick Marryat, and some third-party correspondence of the London publisher Richard Bentley (1794-1871) and Florence Marryat's writing partner Herbert McPherson.
Marryat, Florence, 1833-1899
Marryat, Frederick, 1792-1848
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1833-1905. II. Writings, 1837-1898. III. Performances, 1889-1890. IV. Personal Papers, 1858-1902.
Florence Marryat (1833-1899)
Florence Marryat, English author and actress, was born in Brighton on July 9, 1833, the youngest of the eleven children of English naval officer and novelist Frederick Marryat (1792-1848) and his wife Catherine Shairp (1791-1883). She was married twice, first to Thomas Ross Church (1831-1926), with whom she lived in India for six years, and later to Colonel Francis Lean (1832-1902). Marryat published her first novel in 1865 and produced more than seventy-five titles before her death; most of her books were popular romances featuring strong-minded professional women, including teachers, nurses, and actresses, as their heroines. She also edited the monthly periodical London Society from 1872 to 1876 and published a two-volume biography of her father (1872). Late in life Marryat took to the stage, appearing in roles she created for herself and giving dramatic readings of works by other authors. She died in London on October 27, 1899.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, literary manuscripts, printed ephemera, photographs, drawings and watercolors, scrapbooks, and other papers documenting the life and career of English author and actress Florence Marryat. Visual materials include a wide selection of portraits of Marryat, and drawings and photographs from her time living in South Asia with her first husband; among those are a watercolor portrait of the martyred Sergeant-Major John Lilley (died while imprisioned in Mhow, 1862). Many of Marryat's correspondents were figures in the British literary and theater communities, including Charles Dickens and George Augustus Sala; a scrapbook of letters holds several portrait photographs of those who wrote to her. Also present is material related to Marryat's father, novelist Frederick Marryat, and some third-party correspondence of the London publisher Richard Bentley (1794-1871) and Florence Marryat's writing partner Herbert McPherson.
Authors, English -- 19th century; English literature -- 19th century; Rangoon (Burma) -- Pictorial works; Singapore -- Pictorial works; Tirunelveli (India) -- Pictorial works; Drawings (visual works) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Photographs -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Scrapbooks -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Scripts (documents) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Bentley, Richard, 1794-1871; Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870; Lilley, John, -1862 -- Portraits; Marryat, Florence, 1833-1899; Marryat, Florence, 1833-1899 -- Portraits; Marryat, Frederick, 1792-1848; McPherson, Herbert; Sala, George Augustus, 1828-1895
- Correspondence, 1833-1905; Series I; 13
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains letters sent to Florence Marryat and Frederick Marryat, most of which are housed in a scrapbook at the front of the series.
  - Scrapbook of correspondence, photographs, sketches, and ephemera, 1833-1891 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    General note
    Signatures from a disbound scrapbook containing autograph manuscript letters to Florence and Frederick Marryat from friends, authors, and colleages including Charles Dickens and George Augustus Sala. Some of the letters were written to London publisher Richard Bentley (1794-1871) and were likely acquired by Marryat for their autograph value. Several of the letters have albumen portrait photographs of the letter writer mounted above the letter. The first folder contains two letters from Marryat to her mother. The letters, photographs, and other material remain mounted on their album pages and are in their original order; the fourth folder contains the front and back covers for the album.
  - Bertolotto, Luigi, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dickens, Charles, 1857 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kingsford, Ninon, 1875 Oct 13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Loring, A. K., 1884-1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Neville, George, 1880-1881 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Other letters to Florence Marryat, 1859-1897 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Third-party correspondence
    - Barry, Ethel M., to Herbert McPherson, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Gladstone, W. Z., to Richard Bentley, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Marryat, Frederick, to his sister Fanny Marryat Bury Palliser, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Writings, 1837-1898; Series II; 11
  Series II contains writings by Florence Marryat, her father Frederick Marryat, and others.
  - Writings by Florence Marryat
    - "The Gamekeeper," by Florence Marryat and Howard McPherson; typescript carbon, in four parts, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "The Gamekeeper"; contract, stage play license, letterhead, program, photographs of Brighton, 1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Love Letters," by George Grossmith and Florence Marryat; autograph manuscript, circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writing by Frederick Marryat
    - "Joseph Rushbrook, or the Poacher"; autograph manuscript draft, incomplete, circa 1837 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Other writings
    - "The Duchess of Montemayor," by Frank Rogers; manuscript, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "The Red Phantom"; typescript, corrected, in four parts, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Tiger Bay"; manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Untitled plays and notes; typescript and manuscripts, 1873, undated (Box 2, Folder 21-24)
- Performances, 1889-1890; Series III; 9
  Series III contains material related to Florence Marryat's career as a perfomer. It includes a brochure advertising the programs she created and made available, as well as autograph manuscript and printed texts that she edited, annotated, and used in her dramatic readings.
  - Advertising brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Program for Joseph A. Cave benefit, 1889 Jul 18 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Notebook with various excerpts, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Notebook with various excerpts, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Excerpts from Wilkie Collins, Robert S. Hichens, and others' writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Excerpts from Charles Dickens' writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Excerpt from "Love's Conflict" by Florence Marryat, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Excerpts from Frederick Marryat's writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Excerpts from William Shakespeare's writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Personal Papers, 1858-1902; Series IV; 9
  - Biographical essay by Florence Marryat's daughter, published in St. Paul's, 1899 Dec 30 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Essay on Frederick Marryat's sea novels; author unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Graphics, 1858, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Contains drawings, photographs, and prints; watercolor images include Wimbledon House in Surrey, an unidentified graveyard, a scene in Singapore, and a portrait of Sergeant-Major John Lilley (died in India on May 26, 1862); graphite landscape drawings of Rangoon and Great Britain; salted paper photographs of Tinnevelly (now Tirunelveli), India; and a dried leaf from a "monkey cup" in Bangalore (1858). The drawings are unsigned and undated
  - Portraits of Florence Marryat, 1888, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Includes commercially produced photographs in a variety of formats as well as printed portraits.
  - Portrait photographs of others, 1872, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Printed ephemera, 1880-1896, ndated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - School of Literary Art announcement, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Scrapbook, 1865-1868 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Contains clipped reviews of works by Florence Marryat and others, with three autograph letters, signed, from fans, and two poems in French by Emile de la Roche in honor of Florence Marryat.
  - Will, funeral invitation, and letters to executor Herbert McPherson, 1896-1902 (Box 3, Folder 42)